<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Screenshots of Failing Tests</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Screenshots of Failing Tests">
      <p>
        On some occasions a functional GUI test will run perfectly from within the IDE but will break when executed in a 
        batch with other tests (such as when you are using Ant). This is because functional GUI tests are vulnerable to 
        certain environment-related events, and FEST-Swing is no exception. 
      </p>
      <p>  
        It occasionally may happen that antivirus software runs a scheduled scan while a GUI is under test. If the 
        antivirus software pops up a dialog in front of the GUI, the FEST robot will not be able to access the GUI and 
        will time out eventually, making the test fail. In this case, the failure is not related to a programming error; 
        it is just a case of bad timing. 
      </p>
      <p>
        FEST-Swing is capable of taking a screenshot of the desktop when a GUI test fails, regardless of the test
        framework you use (<a href="http://www.junit.org" target="_blank">JUnit</a> or 
        <a href="http://testng.org" target="_blank">TestNG</a>.) You then can use this 
        screenshot to verify the cause of a failed test and discover whether it is programmatic or environmental.
      </p>
      <p>
        There are many ways to take a screenshot of the desktop when a GUI test fails. Regardless of how the FEST-Swing
        takes a screenshot, it needs to know which tests should be considered &quot;GUI tests.&quot; In order to do so,
        we only need to add the annotation <code class="code">@GUITest</code> 
        (<code class="code">org.fest.swing.annotation.GUITest</code>.) This annotation can be placed at class
        or method level, and it is inherited by subclasses of annotated classes.
      </p>
      <p>
        Once our GUI tests have the <code class="code">@GUITest</code> annotation, we can take screenshot of the desktop
        when a GUI test fails:
        <ol>
          <li><a href="manual-screenshot.html">Manually</a></li>
          <li><a href="junit-screenshot.html">FEST's JUnit extension</a></li>
          <li><a href="testng-screenshot.html">FEST's TestNG extension</a></li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>  
